so without further Ado I wanted to
introduce ramit he has helped lead the
Microsoft app teams there so the first
thing I wanted to get to you and you can
tell us a little bit about your role at
Microsoft but I keep getting people
asking me Microsoft they're like
Enterprise why are you speaking to
Microsoft at an app event and so tell us
a little bit about what you do but then
also like how the apps inside Microsoft
are kind of a startup inside this
massive company yeah thanks a lot for
having me David and hi everyone and
London is Awesome by the way so I'm a
growth lead I'm part of product
management at Microsoft 365 consumer
business so basically our word excel
PowerPoint apps and there's also the
Microsoft 365 app so my current role is
very focused on leading our apps on the
Mac platform I mean Mac app store is a
big part of it we also have a direct
Channel and then I sport IOS and Android
basically our mobile apps as well and we
sell Microsoft 365 personal and family
which is sort of our consumer
subscriptions and then we also sell
co-pilot Pro and we have a fairly large
business on App Store so like straight
up in app purchase business on app store
and we are very much like you guys when
it comes to just growing our apps and
essentially yes Microsoft is an
Enterprise company in a lot of ways but
we are also a very big consumer company
our app presence is actually pretty good
so yeah if you you look at a sensor
Tower a data AI Microsoft apps are some
of the leaders in monetization on the
app store some of the biggest apps some
of the biggest performing apps and
before talking to you I kind of always
thought of it like a lot of the
questions I got this morning about why I
was talking to Microsoft you think of it
as like oh it's an afterthought it's
something Microsoft does because they
have to but the more you and I have
gotten to know each other and talk
through how Microsoft thinks about it
it's pretty cool how you are able to
operate as a startup and how much growth
and monetization you are seeing on the
App Store it's not an after it's
actually like a huge line of bus yeah
and it's a big part of the strategy so
for our consumer business app stores are
very important and we actually have a
pretty decent amount of people and money
that we spend on all the things that are
somewhat covered in this conference like
ASO MMP we have a paid ad strategy we
have a ASO strategy we have teams that
are doing optimization on the funnel so
at all parts activation monetization and
acquisition and renewal optimization and
so on I like to say we have an
equivalent of say Revenue cat and bra
and some app companies inside obviously
we work with a lot of vendors as well so
yeah we have a pretty decent strategy
around that awesome so I wanted to dive
into ASO because I think again even
though it's Microsoft I think we all
have a lot to learn from the strategies
that you and your teams have employed
there at Microsoft but before we go I
know you needed to make a small
disclaimer yes yes so all opinions are
my own and do not represent Microsoft's
official STS so so yeah so that is a
disclaimer that I'm always supposed to
make yeah of course and that's the thing
Microsoft is such a big company there's
so many things going on it makes sense
that we're going to talk about some of
the things you've learned and stuff but
it's not official Microsoft strategy but
on ASO I think a lot of people in this
room again people I talked to this
morning think oh Microsoft can just own
any keyword and like oh it's just all
brand search like people just go and
search word but as you and I have
discussed that's not actually the casee
so tell me a little bit about what kind
of ASO work Microsoft does to find the
right audiences on the App Stores okay
so I mean just like most other app
companies we have a ASO vendor and we
work with them on a number of things and
so if you look at it broadly there's the
brand optimization which we can get
because our apps are named Microsoft
Word Microsoft Excel Etc so like our
brand is very much in the title itself
most of the time so for the keyword
optimization piece we do comparative
keywords so if you look at app stores a
lot of times we are not the number one
productivity app so there are other apps
that are on Mac on iOS also on Android
there are a number of productivity apps
that keep going up and down in the chart
so we have a competitive strategy with
keywords the app stores are kind of a a
great equalizer right yeah it is a
democratic place right so it's not that
you're Microsoft so you can just show up
there and it's not an exclusive to
Microsoft oft channel right so like app
store really democratizes everyone like
just how Paramount Pictures and a
YouTube influencer at the same stage
when it comes to YouTube like in terms
of eyeballs it's the same thing with App
Store like a new app can pretty much get
the top spot we have a comparative
strategy so we always for the most part
know who are the top competitors and
sometimes actually when it comes to App
Store it's not even some of the names
that you would think like I mean sure
there are the big ones like Google canva
Etc but there are a lot of smaller
compar editors smaller apps like
productivity apps that are also at the
top spot so we we do have a strategy to
get some of that keyword so competitive
is a smaller part but actually jobs to
be done is a bigger part of the strategy
so we have like generic and non-generic
keywords so essentially keywords like
notes resumés we have a lot of like user
research around what are our apps used
for because our apps are very general we
try to focus on jobs to be done like
resume creation is a job to be done note
taking a job to be done slide creation
of presentation decks Excel has
budgeting as a big one invoice creation
so those are some of the jobs to be done
that we know so we try to optimize for
some of those keywords because somebody
may be looking for invoice and may end
up at Excel because not everybody is
like a business owner looking for a
QuickBooks type of solution sometimes
you just need something very simple and
Excel can do the job so those are the
kind of things that we keep doing and
there's no like constant set we are
always so every month we have an update
date and our paid ASA also kind of
guides us and also there's this whole
thing that once you are ranked say top
three in a keyword we can remove that
keyword and get new keywords in if
you're seeing that we are consistently
ranked for like say a year or so we can
then you know slowly take that keyword
out and put like an AI or a co-pilot
because we we also have like newer
features and newer things coming in like
AI is a big one so we try to rank for
that and things like that yeah I think
even for smaller and midsize apps
ASO is super competitive so Microsoft
does have an advantage but I mean you
heard it here like on the App Stores you
were competing with the biggest company
in the world you know multi-trillion
dollar company in ASO and so the same
strategies that ramit at Microsoft is
employing is what we all and I have apps
on the App Store as well personally in
addition to working at Revenue cat and
so it's the same kind of strategies we
should all be employing thinking through
the jobs to be done and you were talking
about App Store search ads and I wanted
to touch briefly on how you look at the
profitability of specific keywords and
then how that helps inform your strategy
because I think that's something you
know all app company should be thinking
about I mean there's no one answer
because at any given point of time we
are running multiple campaigns so like
say if we are getting certain keyword
that is really sticky we can always
bring it back but very basic like ASO
101 like the keyword bank is very small
like it's 100 characters and then you
have I mean yes you can stuff a few
things in the description but it also
has to make sense so there is that
aspect that description has to be clean
it has to reflect Microsoft we are not a
junk app that we will write anything in
the app store right so we we have to
make sure that everything that is
external facing is like making a lot of
sense and it's not just keyword
optimization it's not just a bunch of
keywords stuck together so there there
has to be some flow and logic to it but
yeah if we do find from ASA we find some
things that are high performing we can
obviously bring it back to our general
ASO like organic or we can just bid more
there and and there's also the whole MMP
angle there with ASO like trying to
really make sense that if this is the
keyword that is only driving monthly
active usage or is it driving real
subscription because we have very strict
CPI limits like cost per install limits
that we want to kind of go after yeah I
think that's a mistake a lot of folks
make in their ASO strategy is going
after keyword
that are easy to rank for and so like at
Microsoft because the apps get
downloaded so much you could probably
rank for something like swimming but
it's like that's fine but that's not
going to drive business value and so
your ASO strategy shouldn't just be
about ranking but it should be about
using App Store search ads and other
tools to understand the profitability of
the specific keywords and being way more
focused on your approach instead of just
so scattershot do you see any
differences between IOS and Android on
that front are there any differences
there yeah I mean there's the at20 rule
sort of a thing like Android has a very
large install base but we constantly
have seen and so Microsoft apps are
available I believe in six plus app stor
so in China we have a number of app
stores that the apps are available in
there are also pre-installed deals but
still Android monetizes way less than
iOS does so there's a at20 sort of a
thing I mean it's not exactly at20
somewhere like that that Android and
purchase Revenue still lags pretty
significantly to iOS and it becomes
especially interesting from like a LTV
to Mau perspective that for an Android
User for example if you have to run a
paid ads our CPI limits are like 50
times Less in some cases than than iOS
CPI limits right because basically it's
like you can drive installs to Android
and and you can keep getting like more
and more monthly active usage but the
percentage that converts to paying users
is like super super low so so you have
to be so careful with Android both with
cost per install like what you pay from
a paid ad but also sometimes in terms of
your organic strategies so for example
if you have like an engagement platform
that you are paying by I don't know data
points right by data points or by usage
or by Ma you have to be really careful
because your Android campaigns might
start costing you more in terms of cogs
because the LTV because because
essentially if we are selling a consumer
product our ltvs are not like in
thousands of dollars they're in hundreds
of dollars so we are just operating like
any other consumer SAS startup in that
sense that we are making sure that our
LTV to CAC ratios are kind of in range
so that we don't overspend on inapp
engagement or on ads it's not that we
are Microsoft so we'll just like go and
drain money right like so all the same
restrictions apply and It ultimately
comes to the LTV CAC ratio yeah well so
I mean I get asked this all the time you
know oh we've got millions of active
users on Android but it's just not
monetizing how do we improve
monetization like I can now tell them I
talked to ramit from Microsoft and it's
the same thing it's just like Android
does not monetize as well as iOS and
like understanding that reality can help
you inform the Android strategy but then
also Android I think we're going to see
a lot of evolution I'm actually going to
be talking to the Google Play
Partnerships team on a fourth coming
episode where we talk about some of the
experiments that people are starting to
find success with on Android but it's
good to hear from like a prioritization
standpoint that yeah you can put a ton
of work into it and Microsoft has and
has all the resources but it's just a
different platform and it just monetizes
differently and understanding that helps
inform strategy of how you invest how
many data points you collect how you
spend on tooling for Android versus iOS
so super helpful to know another thing I
wanted to dive into was monetization and
AB testing and if there's any particular
tests or anything that you think are
especially interesting on subscription
monetization yeah so before I get into
that I'll finish the Android versus iOS
like I'll just conclude it by saying
that I think Android is a very promising
platform it's just that maybe developers
need to think more than just straight up
expensive subscriptions like because a
lot of the subscriptions are very North
America based I think some of the price
points may need to go down some new
business models may need to be there
like there has to be much more thought
that has to go in to monetize that
platform it's a harder platform to crack
it's you can't just copy and paste your
iOS strategy yes exactly it's it's just
a harder platform to crack and there has
to be more Android specific strategies
that need to get applied I'm not saying
it's not a promising platform I think we
think it's a promising platform form but
there there's just more to be done there
so now moving on to AB testing so yes a
lot of our teams do AB testing on mobile
Microsoft 365 apps like word Exel
PowerPoint as well as the 365 app and
other apps that we have in the family we
keep doing number of experiments and
some of the things that have really
worked just like very plain barebones
ideas that have worked I think CT like
if you have a free trial make sure the C
CS say is it's a free trial like try
free for 1 month something like that
because there's one thing that we have
observed is that CTA has to really
communicate the free value if it's
available so that it's just more
comfortable to press that button right
so basically like you have a free trial
wording up on the top but then you have
say something that says buy now for
example people are just not comfortable
because a lot of times you know because
of how there is like a lot of this one
click buy type of things that have
happened in the recent past like people
are very apprehensive of pressing the
buttons right because they're like oh
I'll just touch this and money will be
charged so if you have a free trial if
you have a more comforting motion like
definitely make sure to have that on the
CTA then another thing we have found a
lot of success with is cards and gifs so
instead of like lines of text using some
kind of cards with gifs what would be in
the GI yeah I I pronounce it gifs but
gifs yeah gifss
potato potato what's in the gifs like an
animation and like demonstrating the
value almost like a little video kind of
yeah sometimes that or sometimes just
illustrations so for a Microsoft 365
subscription some of the more important
things if you open any of our apps some
of our more important things are like
there is the premium apps that you get
on desktop and then there's the one TB
one drive storage that you get and then
there is access to AI features that you
get so those things like you can write
them down or you can actually have like
illustrations showing that you are
getting you know one TB one drive for
each of your family members so you'll
have like six people showing and you see
that one TP one drive is going to all
six of them so if you can show them more
visually it helps in converting better
so that's more of a sort of a pay wall
optimization type of a thing but yeah no
that's a great tip and I I mean I've
been hearing that more I actually I've
been experimenting with a video on my
pay wall in my weather app and have seen
really good results from EXA what you're
saying it's like yeah people just don't
read so you can put all the great like
copyrighting you want but it's like you
got to show them and in the age of Tik
Tok and reals and everything else like
what better way to show them than with
animated video you know illustrations or
other ways to like really capture their
attention and then communicate that
value in a way that they probably won't
read even if you write it very cleverly
so yeah that's a great tip another thing
you had mentioned was experimenting with
just the ordering of subscriptions yeah
yeah so this was a very interesting
experiment where we had our family and
personal so family is slightly more
expensive it's like $9.99 and personal
is a $6.99 subscription in the US and
other region prices are different but so
we just reordered them so we made family
as a default subscription so personal
used to be the default and then we
reordered it and then we did one more
change so actually two separate AB test
so one more change where we started
showing monthly equivalent price so like
if it's $99 for the year then we just
show something like $8 or something like
a monthly equivalent price so both of
those were very successful so monthly
equivalent price when people can see oh
it's just going to cost me $8 even if
they have to be build for the whole year
it's good like we we saw success there
and the second one was yes this
reordering where it was very interesting
that when we reordered both started
selling more and the one that went below
the personal one it actually started
selling a lot more so I think from a
psychological perspective when we were
backtracking maybe there was this whole
idea that people saw this default
subscription which was more expensive
and they're like no no no this is more
expensive but let me get this other one
which is cheaper but it kind of
increased their purchase intent somehow
yeah now the question in that increase
sometimes this is very psychological
like sometimes when you see an expensive
thing like you walk into say like a
Louis Vuitton store you see a lot of
these expensive things and then you end
up buying a tie from there because you
know it's the cheaper thing but you
still bought something from Louis
Vuitton right so it's kind of like that
where you see this more expensive option
up on the top and then you end up buying
the cheaper one because you still bought
something and you still unlocked and you
still have a premium experience so
something like that I didn't plan this
but we ended up talking about pretty
much the top four things that I
recommend people experiment with under
pay walls because like yeah you can test
like colors and change the color of the
CTA button and all that kind of stuff
but like the highest impact are price
testing and included in that the pricing
and packaging like I did a test in my
weather app of defaulting to only
showing the $4 a month subscription
versus showing the $40 a year
subscription and I had a 20% increase in
conversion to paying by them just seeing
that $4 and so by experimenting with the
packaging saw a 20% lift in conversion
to paying and and then the other things
we talked about you experimenting with
video and stuff so these are some of the
lowest hanging fruit not just for any
app here in the audience anybody
listening on the subclub podcast but it
applies to Microsoft as well like the
biggest companies in the world like this
is where the leverage points are on your
pay wall so that's where you should be
experimenting so we are at time but I
did want to give you an opportunity is
there anything you wanted to share as we
wrap up maybe go and download the
Microsoft 365 apps and give us great
reviews and actually you know if you
like them of course yeah know and and I
think everyone here should go download
the apps you know before talking to Ram
I thought oh Microsoft they're just you
know boring Enterprise company but the
more I've talked to ramit The more I've
realized like they're doing really
Innovative stuff and like working hard
at optimization and working on
onboarding and pay wall testing and
packaging testing and so you know when
you're doing research on like best
practices in the industry the apps ramit
works on are actually fantastic examples
of of the type of growth experiments and
the type of onboarding and the type of
things that you want to do in your own
app yeah and let us know what you think
and I'm available on LinkedIn so yeah
happy to help out anybody awesome and
then as we wrap up most of you probably
know I'm with Revenue cat I'm the growth
Advocate we're a subscription management
and optimization platform you know help
simplify billing across iOS Android and
the web and normalize all the crazy
intricacies between IOS and Android so
you can run your CRM campaigns based on
the same toen instead of having to do
different ones for the different
platforms and really help subscription
apps I mean our mission as a company is
to help developers make more money and
so we build the tools to do that I do
bi-weekly interviews with top industry
folks to help subscription apps grow so
check out the podcast on Apple podcast
Spotify or wherever you listen to your
podcast thanks again so much for your
time and for sharing your knowledge and
we'll have to to do some more
collaboration in the future yeah
absolutely and thank you so much David
for having me and thank you everyone for
joining
thanks so much for listening if you have
a minute please leave a review in your
favorite podcast player you can also
stop by chat. sub club.com to join our
private community
[Music]